Functions in Python are defined with that deaf keyword that we saw earlier.
It's followed by a function name, which is a lowercase
separated with underscores, and then parentheses that contain zero
or more arguments and a colon.
Everything that is indented after the function belongs to that function.
So early on in the class, if you remember, we tried to
from future import braces, and we got a no way error never going to happen.
That was a little Easter egg.
Other programming languages like JavaScript use curly braces to
delineate where is the start and end of a function.
Python does not have it. Instead, it relies on weight space.
And so going forward as we start talking about functions,
classes, if statements, you're going to have to be very mindful
of how you use white space, because if things are not
indented at the correct level, you're going to get syntax errors.
If we try to create functions that are missing some of those core components,
so if I try to create a function that does not have that colon,
I'm going to get an invalid syntax.
So, death, the name of the function, parentheses,
colon, and we'll see the Ripple shows us a helpful hint.
Once we have that colon, it's going to turn into dot, dot, dot,
prompt to say, hey, I'm expecting more input here.
In the Ripple, you can just hit a tab.
When I hit enter again, the Ripple is going to say, hey, I'm still waiting for more input.
If you're done defining your function at this point, you can just hit enter again
to get back to that three arrow prompts that we saw earlier.
And that means that the function has now been defined, and it means that I can call it.
When we are writing Python files, this extra new line after the function,
if you don't have it, it's not a syntax error, but pep 8 does state that you should have a new line
after your function definitions, just for readability sake.
You can save the output of calling a function into a variable.
I would have to change my function a little bit, so I would have to change my function to actually
return something, because if I see what is in greeting right now, it's actually going to be a
null value. The function only printed something, it's not returning any values.
So I can redefine my function and have it return a value instead of printing it.
Now when I call my function, it should return the string high, and now I can save that to a variable.
So return statements allow you to do stuff in the function and then pass those values back to the
color. You can return whatever you like. If you're going to be returning more than one value,
you can use it to pull. Now, pretty straightforward calling functions with no arguments.
How do we start making functions that do accept arguments?
We define what arguments we want to accept by separating them with commas,
separating the names that we expect them to be with commas in deeper emphasis.
And then we can use them in our function.
If we wanted to store the value of this, that would be pretty straightforward.
Now result is an integer with 30. We can also have optional arguments and provide a default value for them.
So you would not want to write a function like this in production. Your co-workers would be mad at you.
It is a mystery function that does some weird stuff. But just for the sake of example,
now I can still add my numbers. Let's say 35. I'm actually going to get nine
because there is this default value in z that is one. But I can also pass in my own value for it.
These arguments must be provided because they don't have defaults, providing these arguments is optional.
And they need to be in this specific order.
Required arguments need to be defined first. Optional arguments need to be defined last.
If you mix up the order of these, you're going to get errors.
And it's pretty helpful error. It's a syntax error, not non-default argument,
follows default argument. One more thing about functions is that here we define them
exactly in the order of the, as they were defined in the function. If you provided labels for these,
when you call the function, you can pass, you can pass those in in any order you would like.
So looking at the add numbers function here, I could call add numbers one two and three.
Or I could say that y equals one z equals two and x equals three. And because I've helped
Python out and told it, hey, I'm not calling these in order, but I am giving you the labels.
It's able to figure out what your intent was. Does that make sense?
Okay, cool. Now, we talked about default arguments. We talked about order.
Um, if we try to call a function without all of its default arguments, we're going to get
an exception. So for add numbers, I have two arguments that need to have values x and y.
If I try to call this function with only one value, I'm going to get a pretty helpful error.
It's a type error. It says add numbers is missing one required positional argument of y.
Right? Because I passed an value for this, but not for this. And Python doesn't have a default
value for it. Doesn't know what to do.
If you have arguments that have default values for everything, you can then pass in none of them.
Or some of them. Or all of them. You can mix and match. So we saw we had a create query method.
And I can say that the language is JavaScript by default. And the number of stars is
10 by default. And the sort order is descending by default.
And this is just going to return an epsilon. That says our language is language and
numbers stars is numbers stars and sort is sort.
Now when I call this with no arguments, I get JavaScript. Or I can just provide the language
or I can just provide the number of stars or any mix of them. So these default
arguments are very, very helpful. One thing I want to cover before we move on from arguments is
something that trips up beginners and Python quite a bit. Don't use mutable types as default
arguments. They don't behave the way that you expect.
So if I have a function and I want to have a default argument with a list.
And say, a pen this string to my list. When I call it, when I call this function the first time,
oops. Sorry, I want to go ahead and return that.
So that we can actually see what happens. When I call it for the first time,
it does the right thing. When I call it a second time, there's now two instances of stuff in this
list and then three and then four. Do now use mutable arguments for defaults because the
way that Python works under the hood is these get declared once. So with you do this,
you are going to continue using that very same instance of my list. Every time you call that function,
even though that is not what you intended to do. So this is the source of a lot of subtle
bugs for beginners. So remember, no mutable default arguments. The way that you would want to do this
instead is to have a have a placeholder here where you're using a non-value as a placeholder.
And I'm going to introduce some concepts we haven't talked about yet, but then you can just say
if I've passed an a list, then use it otherwise you can say, if not my list, which means
if it's, if it's, I'm sorry, you want to say, if my list is equal to none, then make a new list
here and then append to it.
Now, when I call do stuff, it's going to do the right thing each time because I took care of
creating the list in this function. I did not pass in an empty list as a keyboard argument.
Wanted only append stuff in the case where my list isn't the file?
Yes. Yeah, just a silly little example.
So, right, I would want to move this over one to the left so that this example worked
when I did pass in a list to start with. Good catch, thank you.
Cool. So, these are arguments and I want to talk about scope a little bit.
There is scope inside of a function. So, I'm going to exit my
Ripple and start it from scratch to clear out everything that I might have defined already.
If I have a function that takes a name and prints it,
I cannot access this name variable outside of the function, outside of this
indented zone because the name is only defined inside of the function.
Once the function exits, that variable doesn't exist. So, Python scope works pretty similar to
scope and other languages. This is something you want to be mindful of.
You want to be very careful when you're using variables inside of a function that are defined
outside of it because if you try to change the value of that variable inside of the function,
the value is only going to apply for that scope. When your function exits,
you're not actually going to be able to modify the value of the variable defined
outside of the function. This can result in some weird subtle bugs. So, here's an example.
And I can say prints out the name outside of the function.
And then I'm going to make a method that says try to change the name.
And I'm going to say that name in the function is max
and print out names inside of the function.
Now, if I call this method, try change name. The name inside of the function is max,
but the name outside of the function is still Nina. So, don't try to change variables in a
function that were declared outside of it. You will have access to them, which can be helpful
if you have like a global variable defined that is like a URL or something that's static,
that's not going to change, but don't try to update it. You're going to end up with some weird
scopeing issues. And so, a use case for using a variable in a function that's decided to
find outside of it is a constant. And to delineate that it's a constant, in that case,
you can name it with all uppercase characters split with a underscore. And that's just
convention. It doesn't mean that there's anything different about that variable.
It's just named a little bit differently in order to signify something to the readers of the program.